So based on what we discussed just now,
what would be the difference between the
three types of practitioners quote
unquote that this is to talk
about and how would you
practically how how would that
practically manifest somebody
dayto-day three times? Yeah. which means
uh so there's faith
type and wisdom type I guess you call it
Well, maybe one difference between the
face type and the wisdom type will be
like the face kind of understood to some
degree some sort of instruction and he
just stick to it kind of regardless of
what his mind shout at him to kind of
refine this understanding. you just keep
to it where like the wisdom type will
have kind of tendency
to try to dig more like what does it
actually mean and how we find they
should be doing that like difference.
So does that mean
that is there any uh
would there be
any fixed characteristic of like
pleasant or unpleasant for one of them?
Yeah, I was kind of going to say maybe
they would almost be characterized by
the dominating hindrances
basically to some degree.
Uh well both both of those yeah would be
mainly characterized by their by the
hes. Um so like
Um so like
well probably the s would be the most
pleasant. That's also what it's said.
So, but so basically with faith type and
and wisdom type, it wouldn't it could be
um pleasant or unpleasant.
Probably it would be unpleasant. Um
because having faith doesn't necessarily
mean that they are
u not acting out of hindrances. You can
be you can be having faith and still be
you know inclining more towards the
direction of engagement in other ways
whereas the wisdom type would be
inclining probably towards engagement in
form in the form of overthinking things.
So that means then that
uh so what what would they each have to
do? Well, the reason I let's say refrain
from trying to clarify things on their
own terms. Let's say like the the
thoughts or doubts they would present
like but is that where they would begin?
Excuse me. Is that where they would
begin? Begin what the train the Yeah.
begin the kind of rebalancing of
their efforts.
I'm not trying to understand like is
that the first point where the restraint
begins? No, obviously the priest. Yeah.
So because see the wisdom
in and of itself, even if they're not
aware of it, would come with the
implication that if I can just
understand this, right? Okay. It doesn't
matter so much. Yeah. Yeah. No, no, no.
Of course, this stuff unless you have
perfected the precepts and are living
srain and what's called mindful of your
intentions, living exclusion and all of
that. Yeah, that would be the requisite for
Yeah, that would be the requisite for
either of the three types basically.
It's not Yeah. So, but the thing is like
still more often than not they would
need to there would be a need to refine
their understanding of what that
training means. Especially if if they
since they will see that the practice is
still being unpleasant
and they're not clear why. It's not that
like they're knowingly kind of
um there is some external reason because
of which they're engaging and they know
that once that finishes they'll go back.
No, it's like even if they wanted the
practice not to be unpleasant but they
don't know how. Uh well that means
probably if they think they're keeping
all these prerequisites then they
probably need to refine their conception
of what it means to be sensor
restrained, what it means to be not
giving into unh wholesome states, what
it means to be in seclusion, all these
things. Um and and their
Um and and their
their task would be then to yeah to um
um
rebalance themselves and
like like I like I was saying before um
create the suitable basis for all these
ideas to be seen on the level where they
need to be
seen which is a mind that has been again
deaggated on a kind of
renunciation not account of something
else. Now what would the samade have to
do? What would be their setback?
kind of laziness, I guess, or laziness.
Well, indulging, I guess, if you could
say, in that can you indulge in in a
state of pronunciation? Well, no. I
mean, more like kind of relaxing, let's
say. Is it that they need to give up
this as people would think? No, but they
would need to bring up maybe things to
think about that.
Uh well that too but what more
specifically would be
like what is it that a puta can become
like super like I mean the Buddhist
teachers uh reaching like the the final uh arupa
uh reaching like the the final uh arupa
attainments like just the limit of where
self view goes like if just one more he
he would have been extinguished.
So why is it that whereas a sautana who
actually understands he might not even
be like even in the first gen. So why is
it that there can be that huge
discrepancy?
What what does cuz it's still delighting
is attainment and to learn how to
relinquish that. But is it like a
conscious like kind
of sensual delight like it's usually
happening with with the absorption
states that people develop or of course
there is delight for anybody who hasn't
freed themselves from craving. But when
you say that way it would almost sound
like like it's a very obvious sort of
like like like um infatuation with it or
something. But the thing is you you get
there by giving up like this course kind
of intoxication with anything pretty
much. Well, I guess maybe you're not
taking that for granted taking that
state to be your result to be
your goal goal of the practice. Take it
to be yours. Yeah. But okay, but sure
those are broader kind of
uh like in in theoretical terms, but
more specifically like what is it that
they're not seeing basically? Let's put
it that way. Yeah. So you're asking what
is it that what is it that the who has
like more somat than than
than what is it that he doesn't see?
What is the kind of small implication
that they will still carry no matter
how kind of deeply they go in that
direction interacting that thing? You mean
interacting that thing? You mean
in general just just what's the wrong
assumption? That just help you. Oh yeah,
of course. But what what what uh how
would that practically manifest in that
specific example?
Is it that just like you tell them like
so could do you think that you could
have somebody who has cultivated somebody but
somebody who has cultivated somebody but
and they know that there is no self
quote unquote. Do you think that would
unquote. Do you think that would
automatically make them be
Well, I don't know cuz cuz they they you
could just take it as information and
then see like, oh yeah, yeah, of course
I already knew that. Yeah, but assuming
that that whole Yono development has
been there because otherwise they
wouldn't be having that somatic to begin
with. Yeah, I know. But okay, let's say
let's put it this way. Imagine you meet
that kind of
person like uh like they have been on
account of some wrong view like in the
Buddhist time. Mhm. some fire worshipper
or something like that or some Brahma
they're living perfectly restrained.
Yeah. Yeah. More more than more than in
our hands like more more secluded more
withdrawn than in our hand. What kind of
instruction would you give them for them
to actually kind of well that they
haven't escaped the real of birth? Okay.
But what does that mean?
Well, that they haven't fundamentally
uprooted being. Yeah. Okay. It's still
an activity like still the Jedi is still
evolutionally produced. So they still
kind of rely on some sort of very subtle
of course but still an activity. Uhhuh.
Okay. But how how do they stop doing
that? Then they just okay I'm not going
to No, they need to they need to
contemplate that any activity is a
burden. Like any form of activity
regardless of the how subtle it is
regardless like the whole picture it is
kind of a burden regardless.
And what what would be the goal of that
discernment? Non attachment to the pleasure even
Non attachment to the pleasure even
though those
states and then it's done. Okay. But what what
and then it's done. Okay. But what what
other see the thing is there's something
more specific there that that is
problematic. something that they wouldn't be seeing.
something that they wouldn't be seeing.
somebody who goes all the all all the
way to uh what is it perception or
nonperception but asina and now you're
asking what is it that they are not
seeing that you can get something yeah
but but that's what is it that like what is
but that's what is it that like what is
it
that's what is it that they take for
granted let's
say as
as important
Well, for example, that thing that left
see why let's say why is it let's phrase it
why let's say why is it let's phrase it
this way. Why is it
that the feder of sabata praamasa
wouldn't be overcome in the in the
because sabata paramasa doesn't just
mean the rights and rituals that we
often say it's the right right uh virtue
the right duties of being secluded you
know uh restraining your speech and all
this stuff that would actually lead to
this um peace of states is it like I
have to do it yeah but I have to like I
have to keep those things. I have to
engage. The thing is if you just like if
you just tell stop thinking I am this
like they can easily they can easily kind of
they can easily they can easily kind of
oh yeah yeah okay okay because see they
have already developed a degree of
giving up. So it's like they can even
think that that's what they're already
doing. So, you have to phrase it in more
accurate terms that would like directly
cut through their assumption and the
thing that they're emphasizing. And I
think I actually already mentioned it a
few times, but uh
it seems it didn't fully make the
connection between. Is it to make them
recognize that this state is like
dependently a reason?
Yeah. But like let's say let's not put
the emphasis on the states. that let's
say um how they are living their lives.
No, no, no, no, no, no. Right, right,
right. That even this state that they
have developed is dependent on this
lifestyle that taking for granted the
given state of affairs the way that it
is basically like a healthy body for
example. Yes. That would bring them
closer to Yeah. So then they don't see
impermanence in an Yeah. Well, they see
impermanence in regard to everything
else except
this like they have reached that state
by seeing the impermanence
of sensual pleasures. Mhm. Because the
sutas describe like these aesthetics um
not in during the Buddhist time but
before they would they would factually
like reach the Brahma realm and so on
because they they develop the
understanding of sensuality as
impermanent. They would they would be
and they would be preaching that as
their dharma but it would stop there.
Yeah. So they would see the impermanence
of that too. But now the point is like
sure that's just an answer that somebody
can read the suta and they just say oh
yeah they they need to see that state
too as impermanent. But what I'm saying
is what is it that could you you could
point them to to like really make
sure that their understanding is
important because again they could just
assimilate that view and say oh yeah
yeah okay yeah of course it's it's
impermanent because Yeah. So then it
stays on on the level of information.
Yeah. So how could how would you tell
them like if you understood it as
impermanent, if you actually understood
is impermanent. Mhm. What would happen? Complete dispassion,
Complete dispassion,
which would mean that
they don't care whether it's coming back
or not. Exactly. So that's that's that's
what I was trying to get to. So like
they would still be carrying the
implication that if even if they think
they're free from suffering because the
sut would say like bajia and stuff he
was exactly that position where he was
probably unthinkable that he he would
have been thinking that unless he had
developed his mind in in in these ways
but um yeah unless they
um yeah unless they
recognize that actually it doesn't
matter Because you can have all the views of
Because you can have all the views of
like, oh yeah, it's impermanent and it's
like this and it's like that. But as
long as there's that implication that
only if I have
this will I be in the right kind of
position will I be practicing rightly to
that extent you haven't understood that
this is not worth holding on to and it's
not where the purity comes from. Mhm.
And for as long as that's the case, you
will also have seen a lot of
paramas because your peace will depend
like you said on the lifestyle that
produced that enables the state. So it's
not that that virtue that they were
keeping that would give rise to this was
wrong and they should stop doing it.
It's the fact that if they recognize
that a peaceful mind
isn't what isn't what freedom from
suffering is, isn't what nibbana is, if
they were to understand
that, they would keep the virtue with a
completely different attitude, they
would keep the virtue without any fear
of what would happen if they don't keep
the virtue because they're not afraid of
the agitated mind.
But if their notion of peace is is
intrinsically bound up with this pure
state that they have cultivated,
inevitably they will be afraid of what
will happen if they give up all of the
right training that they've been
cultivating and let's say not fully
start engaging in sensuality or
something but just go back to a precepts
and uh live in a crowded environment
which again an arroant could also
if there's some reason for it or some
accident or something and they just
can't live in the monastery anymore.
Um like if if this if if if all these
prerequisites were to be destroyed and
the state were to be destroyed, they
would feel like they lost their freedom
because it was bound up with with all
this. And see that's that's how you
that's what it means to say that it's
dependently arisen. But the problem is
like nowadays these ideas are so kind of
when a Buddha said them it was
revolutionary. So like somebody hears
that and they would be forced to think
about it. It's like oh yeah what huh
what does he mean with that? But
nowadays you just say say to someone and
whoever has any inkling of spirituality
would have heard that before and they
would just say they might even have
cultivated the state by practicing
something like that. And they will think
like oh yeah of course yeah yeah yeah of
course it's dependent
but no it's like accurately speaking if
you were to actually understand that
then why cuz they would realize actually
why cuz they would realize actually
sometimes I'm even
prioritizing things that are necessary
for this calm to come about but are not
fully indispensable to be free from
video vision and
delusion like avoiding all talk avoiding
all sleep all speech. The Buddha didn't
do that.
So avoiding um criticizing others
because that would probably and avoid
avoiding discussions and and um kind of
engaging in in indepth uh conversations
about dharma. The Buddha didn't avoid
those things because he understood that
even when the mind would get slightly
kind of
um fall back basically from the state of
samadi that that depends on seclusion he
wouldn't suffer on account of this but
somebody who whose sense of identity
literally depends on on on having that
withdrawn mind all the time they would
feel like oh yeah I always need to be
living this super um tight lifestyle of
of not just again the precepts but like
all of this other uh
layers of um withdrawal added to it. So,
and that's why then the Buddhist told
Mahakasupa that oh just just come back
and and live in the palace
because you don't need you don't need um
the the seclusion and the like living in
that cave where he was that he had to
like walk up your job is done. Yeah. He
he had to like walk up this this huge
hill just to reach that cave where he
was living like completely withdrawn
from from people.
And then he said it's it's for the
example to give a good example to next
generations and for his pleasant abiding
here and now that he would continue to
do it because he realized oh yeah
inevitably even being in our hands if we
were to go back to that more engaged
lifestyle um and meeting people all the time and
um and meeting people all the time and
all this stuff uh that pleasant abiding
would deteriorate. But see it it didn't
say like oh I won't do it because I need
this. Mhm. No. So, in his case, it was
just a preference. Yeah. But, uh, but if
it for some reason he got sick and he
had to not live up there anymore and and
and just just live in a more crowded
place, he wouldn't suffer even if then
his his body deteriorates. Yeah. So,
there's basically and it also so there
would be no fear as you mentioned
earlier and that sometimes indeed told
us also the sut say like free from greed
and illusion and fear. Yeah. Yeah. So
because if there's anything that you
hold on to even if it's the things that
are beneficial for the practice to that
extent you will suffer. It's a better
attachment than all the others because
this one is takes you closer to nibbana
rather than away from it. But if you
just stay there it's kind of like kind
of like
um you just moved all the
way to like the
crossing point.
And then you just stay there. You could
have just But no,
you stay there and uh then you die and
and I guess nobody tells you like wait
no no no just one step more. Don't don't
stop. Um then uh you yeah there there no
indication that you're not suffering
anymore. So why why would you keep
trying to do to do anything more?
But so there's this suta somewhere.
There's this sick monk basically dying,
I think. And the Buddha comes and he
asks him how he's doing. He's like,
"Yeah, I'm not doing very well." And he
says, "Okay. Well, I hope you're at
least free from remorse." And I said,
"No, no, no, I'm not free from remorse."
And he said, "Why?" Well, because I fell
away from the thing. So are you saying
that monk did not even have that you or
could someone with that? No, there could
still be there could still be there
could still be some slight emphasis of
of
uh like uh the only when when it's when
it's because there's still conceit and
and kind of identification with the
aggregates. So they could still
have a a sense that that they need to
have peaceful mind in order to to uh of
course they would see through it like if
if if eventually they would that's the
difference like if they were just to
practice long enough it would become
clear that they have to apply the same
principle of of they just they just
wouldn't be able to hold on to it
to anywhere near the same degree as
somebody who doesn't have the right
view. Um but yeah that's why it it does
say that that once they develop it well
enough then they need to contemplate
that that's also impermanent and all
that not because they are like the other
person implying that it's actually
eternal like those brahas they would
actually have the view that like no this
is kind of overdoing the
the kind of
uh finding safety in it. They they know
that there is like as to say somebody
accomplishing you is incapable of taking
any sankara as permanent any sankara as
pleasant and any dharma as self. So they
cannot have the view mhm that it's that
it's otherwise but there can still be
just by not being fully clear that it's
like not just impermanent but as it says
it's like a dart a boil an arrow. it's a
calamity, a disaster. Um, then they
aren't fully they aren't fully turn away from
fully they aren't fully turn away from
the entire extent of the arguments
basically.
So back to your question
of what does a well a faith type and a
wisdom type and a type what do they have
to do in order
to overcome the shortcomings
corresponding shortcomings. Yeah. Would
a sort of simple answer to that be to
try to understand what the other two
types are and to try to emulate them? In
a way that could be that could be a a
good way to look at it. Um
because yeah it would be like
um if if actually no there's even that
suta where it says somebody who is
accomplished in
uh discernment should go and ask
somebody who is accomplished in coming
how how to calm the mind. somebody who
is accomplishing discernment uh in come
should go and ask somebody. It says how
should you regard saras in order to
develop discernment basically. Uh and um
and so that would
be yeah that would be the way to
to kind of um fill out the the things
that they haven't sufficiently
cultivated. So in the case of the wizard
type, yeah, it would just be like, okay,
how do I kind of keep myself in check
not to drift away into some sort
of
random distractions, even if they seem
justified of like thinking about dhamma
and stuff or the faith type distractions
of who knows like helping the teacher or
something just just overly kind of like
let me take care of this. Do you want me
to uh renew the whole you want do you
want the new um do you want the new
bathroom? So
um then then uh for this mind type then
it would just be yeah
like actively
clarifying the nature of their
experience in such a way that even when
they're not at peace they still wouldn't
suffer. to kind of take away the
emphasis from from the from the piece
and see like no how can I uh not suffer
even amidst suffering so that you know
even if I were to just again
completely like live in this crowded
environment in a hospital or something
that I that even then I wouldn't
suffer how could I how could I see
myself how could I develop such
understanding that I don't suffer even
when I'm going around left and right
like this other guy